Guide to the Mel Shimm Papers, 1954-1990 UA.29.02.0262
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Mel Shimm Papers
1954-1990
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
UA.29.02.0262
3.0 Linear Feet
Mel Shimm was a professor of law and Associate Dean at the Duke Law School. The Mel Shimm papers include materials from Mel Shimm's time as a faculty member at Duke Law School. Included are class materials such as exams and readings, correspondence, committee materials, and other materials.
Biographical / Historical
Melvin G. Shimm was born January 30, 1926 to Joseph and Sadie Shimm in New York City. He served in the Army during World War 2, then graduated from Columbia University in 1947. He then graduated from Yale Law School in 1950 before practicing law in New York City and Washington, D.C. He became a professor of law at the University of Chicago in 1952 before coming to Duke University in 1953. He was a member of the faculty of the Duke Law School until his retiredment in 1996, and he served as the Associate Dean of the Law School from 1978-1983. He served as the editor of Law and Contemporary Problems, as faculty editor of the Duke Law Journal, and edited the Journal of Legal Education, as well as non-Duke publications such as the Journal of Business Law and Business Law Review. He was also the Director of the Duke Summer Institute in Transnational Law from 1986-1992. He won the Mordecai Society Award in 1960, the Duke Law School A. Kenneth Pye award in 1999, and the Duke University Award for Merit in 1996. In 2000, an endowed professorship in the Duke Law School was named for him.
Mel Shimm married Cynia Brown (Dr. Cynia B. Shimm), a psychologist who also taught Pscyhology for Lawyers with Mel Shimm at Duke Law School. The couple had two sons, David and Jonathan. Mel Shimm died on September 17, 2005.
Access Restrictions
This collection has not been processed or screened for protected information, and may need to be reviewed before use.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Mel Shimm Papers were received by the Duke University Archives as a transfer in 2017.
Related Materials
School of Law Reference Collection, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
School of Law Records, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
A. Kenneth Pye, Chancellor, Records and Papers, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Collection Overview
The Mel Shimm papers include materials from Mel Shimm's time as a faculty member at Duke Law School. Included are class materials such as exams and readings, correspondence, committee materials, and other materials.
Law -- Study and teaching -- North Carolina -- Durham; Estates (Law); Shimm, Melvin G.; Duke University. School of Law -- Faculty
- unfoldered materials (Box 1)
- Board of Adjustment, 1967-1968 (Box 1)
- Board of Adjustment, 1965-1966 (Box 1)
- Board of Adjustment, 1969-1970 (Box 1)
- Curriculum Committee, 1970-1972 (Box 1)
- Curriculum Committee, 1965-1970 (Box 1)
- Law School Curriculum Committee, 1957-1965 (Box 1)
- Law School Building Committee (Box 1)
- Faculty-Student Relations Committee (Box 1)
- Joint Degree Program - Law School and Institute of Policy Science and Public Affairs (Box 1)
- Combined Medical-Legal Education Committee (Box 1)
- Law School Library Committee (Box 1)
- Legal Aid Committee (Box 2)
- Placement Committee (Box 2)
- unfoldered materials (Box 2)
- untitled (Box 2)
- Dean Selection (Box 2)
- Law School Long-Range Planning Committee (Box 2)
- unfoldered materials (Box 2)
- untitled (Box 2)
- Debtor's Estates (1 of 4) (Box 2)
- Debtor's Estates (2 of 4) (Box 2)
- Debtor's Estates (3 of 4) (Box 2)
- Debtor's Estates (4 of 4) (Box 2)
- untitled (Box 2)
- untitled (Box 2)
- untitled (Box 2)
- unfoldered materials (Box 2)
- untitled (Box 3)
- untitled (Box 3)
- Miscellaneous Correspondence: Memos (Box 3)
- Exams with Class Lists (Box 3)
- Miscellaneous exams (Box 3)